<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
<header>
    <title>Hoard Frequently Asked Questions</title> 
</header>

<body>
  <section>
<title>
What kind of applications will Hoard speed up?
</title>
  <p>
Hoard will always improve the performance of multithreaded programs
running on multiprocessors that make frequent use of the heap (calls
to malloc/free or new/delete, as well as many STL functions). Because
Hoard avoids false sharing, Hoard also speeds up programs that only
occasionally call heap functions but access these objects frequently.
  </p>
</section>


  <section>
<title>
  I'm using the STL but not seeing any performance improvement. Why not?
  </title>
      <p>
In order to benefit from Hoard, you have to tell STL to use malloc instead of its internal custom memory allocator:
      </p>

<source>
typedef list&lt;unsigned int, malloc_alloc&gt; mylist;
</source>

</section>


<section><title>
What systems does Hoard work on?
</title>
  <p>
Hoard has been successfully tested on numerous Windows, Linux and
Solaris systems, including a 4-processor x86 box running Windows
NT/2000, a 4-processor x86 box running RedHat Linux 6.0 and 6.1, and a
16-processor Sun Enterprise server running Solaris.
  </p>
</section>


<section><title>
Have you compared Hoard with SmartHeap SMP?
</title>
  <p>
We tried SmartHeap SMP but it did not work on our Suns (due to an
apparent race condition in the code).
  </p>
  </section>


  <section>
<title>
      Have you compared Hoard against mtmalloc or libumem?
</title>
<p>
Yes. Hoard is much faster than either. For example, here's an
execution of threadtest on Solaris:
</p>
      <table>
           <tr>
             <td>Default:</td>
 	     <td>4.60 seconds</td>
           </tr>
           <tr>
             <td>Libmtmalloc:</td>
 	     <td>6.23 seconds</td>
           </tr>
           <tr>
             <td>Libumem:</td>
             <td>5.47 seconds</td>
           </tr>
           <tr>
             <td>Hoard 3.2:</td>
 	     <td>1.99 seconds</td>
           </tr>
     </table>
</section>

<section>
<title>
Can I use Hoard with a commercial application?
</title>
<p>
Yes. Hoard is available under two licenses. The first license is the
GNU General Public License. That license is free, but it requires you
to open-source your application. The second option is to purchase a
license from the University of Texas at Austin. Click the "Licensing Info"
link on the left for more information.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
